Are we ready?
Okay, let's do this. And action. Let's
head over to Notebook LM. This is kind
of like a sweeping request for tell me
what to do. Give me your best advice
based on everything I've given you.
Wow.
So I often express an intention for work
life balance but then what I actually do
I I feel that at a deep
level coaching can be life-changing but
it's also expensive. I found that one of
the most important things in good
coaching is context. It's important that
the coach knows about you, your goals,
your opportunities, both your strengths
and your weaknesses, how your mind
works. Well, we live in a time when AI
has an essentially unlimited context
window. So, in this video, I'm going to
sit down with Notebook LM and load up 40
separate documents containing almost
150,000 words, which is everything that
I have and everything that I know about
how I work inside. And we're going to
find out whether AI can become a coach
for you in your life or in your work and
exactly how to go about doing that step
by step. Let's get into it. Let's talk
about the sources that I'm going to be
loading up into it. And they fall into
three categories. The first one is
private notes. Your personal private
notes are really one of the best
sources. Most people don't have a lot of
public writing, don't necessarily do
annual reviews, but we all have notes.
It might be something as simple as some
text from an email you sent a friend in
the past or something you've jotted down
in your Apple Notes. Notes have this
quality of being very honest, very
vulnerable because you have no
expectation of ever sharing them. And
it's perfectly fine if they're messy all
over the place with typos. AI can handle
all of that and see through all of the
messiness and still make use of those
notes. So these private notes contain
things like all of the notes from my
coaching sessions with my human coach
over the past few years, images which
Notebook LM can now understand. There's
a mind map that I update every year with
my life goals, my big five personality
traits, which I have uh from a survey,
and then what's called my time
perspective, which is from a book by an
author named Zambardo, which is about my
relationship to time. I also have a
collection of my strengths based on
years of customer testimonials that I've
collected. I have a compilation of all
my gratitude lists, which is something
that I do at the end of every year. I
just make a big list of everything that
I'm thankful for. and also myersbrig
profile. And if you're curious how I
have all these notes, check out my book
and course and membership called
Building a Second Brain, which is all
about how to create an effective
note-taking system. Next, we have my
public writing from takeaways from
courses I've taken to my experience at
Burning Man to summaries of books that I
found compelling, writing I've done
about sort of my autobiography, my life
story, a list of my favorite open
questions. So these are all public
sources that I've written about
different aspects of how I think about
life and where I want to go in life and
where I've been. And then the third
category is also a ritual that I perform
at the end of every year which is my
yearend review or yearin review. And
that's simply a practice that I do every
December where I write about what
happened that year. What were the high
points, the low points, the takeaways,
the lessons learned. So you can see I
have chosen and linked to the last five
years because I want my coach to take
that into account and to guide and help
me and support me towards achieving
those things. So now let's head over to
Notebook LM. You'll notice that I'm
using the paid version, Notebook LM
Plus, which is about $20 per month. And
as always, I'm going to start by
creating a new project. If you're
curious how I'm actually doing this
loading up of sources one by one, check
out this previous video where I cover
that in depth. Now, this is the part
that's a little bit timeconuming and
we're going to speed through the process
of individually selecting each of those
sources that I've prepared and loading
them up into this project in Notebook
LM. Would you be willing and open to
load up really some of your most
personal sensitive material and
introspection to AI? Well, here I am
testing it for you to
see. All right. Okay. So, that took me
about 17 minutes. Uh, definitely took
some effort. If you look here in the
left side panel, I have about 40
different sources totaling more than
150,000 words. Think about how sci-fi
and futuristic this is that I can just
sit here and load all this up and now
I'm just going to have a conversation
drawing on over 150,000 words of my
personal context and life story. Just
completely mind-blowing. Let's just
recognize that fact for a second. The
next step here is to start asking
questions. Let's head over to the Google
doc that I prepared beforehand again.
And here I have about 30 questions, many
of which actually came from my previous
conversations with AI models. You can
find a list of the questions that I used
in this demonstration at this QR code or
in the description below. So let's start
with this one right here. So I'll copy
that, head over here, paste it into the
chat window. So for strengths, it
identifies knowledgeable and deep
understanding, visionary and futuristic
thinking, creativity, being innovative,
insightful, and perspective. It's
interesting. There's not really any new
information here, but what I'm kind of
looking for is just to make sure that
the AI is working. So let's look at
weaknesses. And this is where I'm a
little bit nervous to see what it came
up with. Self-criticism and
perfectionism. That's absolutely true.
It notes that that is a common weakness
for myersbrig profile which is INFJ. So
that kind of oddly makes me feel a bit
better that it's kind of characteristic
of my personality type. Sensitivity to
criticism and conflict. Tendency towards
idealism and overlooking details
definitely. Um social skills it says is
a perceived challenge. That's
interesting. So maybe it's not uh based
in reality. It's just kind of how I see
myself. emotional vulnerability,
resistance to emotional processing. Uh
specifically when it comes to the past,
uh I'd say for sure uh potential for
being overly private. I don't know about
that one. I tend to share quite a bit
publicly. Taking on too much
responsibility, fear of being ordinary,
uh overthinking and analysis paralysis.
I mean, this is the most thorough and I
would say accurate list uh of my
weaknesses I think I've ever seen. Next,
I want to know what have been my
recurring challenges or obstacles. So,
let's copy that. I'm just going to go
ahead and paste that. So, this is
interesting. It's a lot of the same
things as my weaknesses, but there's
also some different things such as fear
of failure or fear of not achieving
enough. That is not exactly a weakness.
It's more like a recurring challenge
that comes from the weakness of uh being
too self-critical. It's drawing on some
of my writing about my personal
development that I've done. It's drawing
on my coaching notes with my human
coach. You'll notice that the first few
questions that I asked were sort of just
getting a lay of the land, just asking
the AI to repeat back to me or to
summarize or to distill what it sees in
my life story. But now I'm going to sort
of make a turn to a different kind of
question which is much more subjective
and much more interpretive and really
draws on things like judgment and even
wisdom. So I think this will be the real
challenge to see if AI can not just
summarize stuff but actually give me
advice and point out insights or blind
spots that I might not even be aware of
myself. Are there any contradictions
between my stated intentions such as my
goals and what I actually do and the
results that I've achieved? Oh boy, here
we go. So, based on the sources, there
appear to be several contradictions
between your stated intentions and your
actions or results. Looks like I often
express an intention for work life
balance, but then what I actually do
prioritizes work. Ouch. It's noting that
I tend to
compartmentalize and derive a lot of joy
and creativity from my work, but then
have trouble spreading that to other
places such as my home and work life.
That hurts, but it is definitely
accurate. So, despite expressing those
intentions throughout several of my
annual reviews, I make a clear emphasis
on business growth and achievement,
often at the expense of personal time
and well-being. It does say that later
reviews show more awareness and
intention in this area. Great. Looks
like there's a tension between wanting
to delegate, for example, to people on
my team, but also difficulty letting go
of control. In some cases, even refusing
help from others. And that tension leads
to this persistent question which I have
to this day, which is how to inspire
greatness in others without me being
directly involved. Looks like I have a
tension between uh a desire for
financial prudence and keeping spending
in check versus being quite a free
spender, which I would say is definitely
the case. It even has the context to
know that that free spending was partly
a reaction against my father's
frugality, which is pretty deep. There's
a tendency between focus and chasing uh
shiny objects. There's a tension between
wanting sustainable growth but also
experiencing burnout, between being
present with my family and being
distracted by work. So this is again
just an excellent uh distillation of I
would say most if not all of the key
tensions that I keep returning to again
both in my work and in my life. Now I'd
like to know about blind spots or
limiting beliefs. And what I really am
going to look at here is if there's
anything that I haven't heard of before
or I'm not aware of. Interesting that
it's now drawing not just on the sources
that I loaded up, but our own
conversation history, which is mostly
things that it has said. So what I
assume that means is it can now draw on
its previous responses and my previous
questions to come up with sort of second
order insights. The one thing I'm seeing
here that I hadn't considered is that I
tend to avoid disappointment. The
feeling, the emotion of disappointment,
which paradoxically can create more
disappointment. So, I'm actually going
to highlight that and then save it as a
note over here on the right because I
want to revisit that a bit later.
Something I'm realizing is it's getting
a little bit repetitive. It's actually
just restating some of the same findings
and observations just in different ways,
using different language. Let's see what
else here could potentially be valuable.
Here's a good one. Based on these notes,
when have I been the happiest? Uh, this
is actually one I think I got from a
friend, so it has a little bit more
instructions. It says, "Please be
specific about moments and situations.
Identify what specifically caused the
happiness. Be truthful and don't make
anything up. And if you find a specific
moment of happiness, don't summarize it.
Find moments that are surprising. So
these are all great tips that you can
use in your own conversations with AI.
So it's citing a meditation retreat that
I went on and specifically day nine. So
I experienced waves of pleasure starting
throughout my body completely on their
own. That's fascinating. So what this is
kind of reminding me of is how much
meditation is good for me. I've kind of
let meditation as a habit fall by the
wayside in recent years, but based on
this, I think I actually want to bring
that back as part of my say morning or
evening routine. I'm also seeing some
stuff about past uh experiences with
psychedelics with iawasa which is kind
of reminding me I think I would like to
revisit some of that maybe do some
psilocybin or MDMA assisted therapy
which I know is becoming more and more
popular. It's also reminding me of some
really beautiful moments with my uh kids
when they were babies, as well as how
happy I am when I do many consecutive
hours of deep reading and writing. It's
reminding me how much I love and how
much I get from deeply immersive and
intentional spaces with fellow
entrepreneurs and creators. So, mostly
what I'm getting from this is just
reminders.
You know, I've had a lot of moments in
the past that I was deeply satisfied and
deeply happy. So maybe it's as simple as
just recreating and revisiting some of
those same kinds of situations. So
here's a really interesting one. What is
obvious to everyone around me, but
doesn't appear obvious to me? So it
suggests that I may be underestimating
the team's capabilities. That's one that
I want to highlight and save as a note
to revisit. It even says the possibility
you're already making a significant
positive impact. So maybe I should just
relax. I mean that's definitely the
case. Oh, and interesting. It notes that
my kind of attempt to reinvent myself
and reinvent my my career and my
business that others around me might not
clearly see the shift. I had never
considered the impact on the people
around me of this more or less constant
need to reinvent what I'm doing. So I
think I'll save that one as well. So
what's so interesting about this is at
this stage this is so actionable. I can
go online and I could do a search for
courses or programs or coaches who could
help me develop these very specific
skills. All right. So this last batch of
questions is kind of pivoting from the
past and the present which is mostly
what we've been talking about. But where
coaching is the most powerful where the
value is really the clearest is when it
comes to the future, future goals,
future projects, future decisions,
future milestones. So let's dive into
some of these questions. Oh, this is one
I think about a lot. If I were to regret
something at the end of my life, what
might that be? So the headline here is
not fully prioritizing meaningful
relationships and a balanced life and
instead overemphasizing work and
external achievements at the expense of
deeper connections and personal
well-being. Wow.
So that actually really like hits me. I
I feel that at a deep level because this
is kind of like the big fear that I that
I'm afraid I'll end up with on my
deathbed that I made that trade-off
between meaningful relationships and
balance and work and external
achievements on the other hand
incorrectly inappropriately. This is
kind of the most succinct
uh summary or distillation of my I would
say my core fear in life that I think
I've ever seen. But wow, I kind of want
to save this sentence right here in bold
for really some deep reflection and
processing over what I want to change at
this stage, you know, at the midpoint of
my life so that I don't end up on my
deathbed feeling this way. Next, I'm
going to ask based on all my sources,
all the questions I've asked in this
chat and your responses, what is your
best advice for how I should approach
goals and challenges in both my personal
and professional life? So, this is kind
of like a sweeping request for tell me
what to do. Give me your best advice
based on everything I've talked about
and everything I've given you.
Interesting. Prioritize self-nowledge
and authenticity. Really asking myself,
what do I truly want? question the
narratives and stories I tell myself.
Embrace emotional intelligence and
integration. Moving towards areas where
you feel shame with curiosity and
openness. I think that's advice I've
actually given to myself at some point
in my writing, but seeing it reflected
back is actually helpful. Strive for
integration rather than
compartmentalization. So, I think I'll
save that one because I want to ask more
about it. Value relationships and
community. Adopt a growth oriented
mindset. Embrace vulnerability and
imperfection. define enough and
prioritize balance. So, what strikes me
with these is I think you could give
this advice to almost anyone. It's a
little bit maybe generic in that sense,
but that doesn't mean it's not true and
doesn't mean it's not helpful. I think
what I would ask of a human coach is to
start to go deeper into some of these
and really apply them to like my
specific circumstances right now. How
I'm spending my days, the projects I'm
working on, my my just day-to-day
circumstances. And the final question is
I want to know if there's any question I
should have asked. What question did I
not ask in our conversation that might
yield a novel insight that hasn't come
up yet? So I'm specifically asking it
for something that hasn't been addressed
previously. Interesting. So I've
expressed a difference in kind of
somatic healing and somatic exploration.
So that is a current interest and it's
asking what physical sensations so very
specifically and recurring bodily
experiences might be offering you
insights into your current goals,
challenges or unagnowledged desires.
That is an interesting question. I had
never thought to try to tie specific
physical sensations directly to insights
and takeaways for uh my goals and
challenges and unagnowledged desires. So
I think I'm just going to copy that
question and now ask it. Okay. Wow. So I
think this is the most interesting and
relevant thing that we've covered so
far. Uh and it kind of makes sense.
We've kind of explored so many aspects
of myself built on things we've talked
about before. I asked it which question
I should ask and then the AI suggested a
question and then I asked that question.
So it kind of makes sense that we've
arrived essentially at the frontier of
my own personal development and my
growth as a person. So it's really the
specificity of this. It's it's almost
like a series of practices or a di again
a set of diagnostic criteria that I
could look at uh such as tension or
tightness in specific areas and it gives
some examples of which emotions those
might correspond to changes in energy
levels, digestive issues which I have
been having lately. I had not thought
that those could be related to uh things
like my psychology and my emotions and
even give some examples. Heart related
sensations, racing heart, heavy chest,
feeling of expansion or warmth, changes
in breathing patterns, temperature
changes, uh recurring aches or pains
which I have been having a few. And it
even goes beyond that. you know, if I am
wondering how do I actually explore
these things or get in touch with them,
it suggests a apparently like an
existing practice called active body
awareness, which I hadn't really heard
of before that specifically. And it
suggests throughout your day, pause and
notice what physical sensations you're
experiencing without judgment. And it
asks these questions. So, this is an
incredibly I mean this list of questions
I could I could actually sit down and in
five minutes ask one or two of them and
um actively bring this thing called
active body awareness which I hadn't
known about into my routine and into my
day. Uh, I could even fire up AI, uh, or
talk it over with a human being and
actually explore, say, one of these
questions in more depth and do kind of
like a conversational journaling with
something like Notebook LM and thus make
it not just an intellectual exercise,
which I know based on our conversation
is not very effective for me, uh, but
actually make it a two-way conversation
so that it integrates at a deeper level.
And that's it. So, we've spent quite a
bit of time here exploring my inner
world. I thank you for your patience and
being willing to go on that little
journey with me. And revisiting my
original question, which was, can AI be
an effective coach for me, I noticed a
couple things. I would say from the
level of information and knowledge that
it actually performed very very well. In
just a matter of a couple hours of
preparation plus 15 minutes of loading
up those sources into notebook LM, I've
done the equivalent of probably 10 or 15
years of context building that would be
required with a human. The fact that it
can hold in its mind, in its memory, so
to speak, such a vast amount of just
details, such amount of specifics, even
more than I can hold in my head about
myself, means that it could pretty
effortlessly go from big picture 10,000
ft view perspectives immediately and
instantaneously down to the most
specific thing I mentioned in one
sentence of one article or blog post
that I've written. That is something
that a human being, a human coach cannot
do. What it's not doing so well and
really what are some of the most
valuable moments with my human coach
have to do with the emotions. And often
that is something as simple as that
human, that person seeing a micro
expression on my face, seeing my body
language, whether we're working together
on Zoom or in person, noticing when I
make a pause or when I kind of uh have a
certain reaction to something that she
said. a lot of that kind of uh subtle or
um body language or not explicit
information is some of the most valuable
information. So I think the way that I
would use AI in the future is not as a
replacement for a human coach. It's not
at the point where it can seamlessly
take the place of at least a highly
skilled and experienced coach, but I
would say it's an excellent compliment.
In fact, one of the most useful and
commonly cited sources in this
conversation was that document with
several years of notes from my coaching
sessions with my human coach. So, I
would say that these two forms of
coaching, these two relationships are
highly complimentary. They strengthen
each other. They make each other better.
So, it's not about choosing one or the
other. It's about using what AI and
technology is really good at alongside
and in conjunction with what human
beings are good at, which is that
personal, relational, and intuitive
emotional aspect. I invite you to try
this for yourself. You can use any of
the AI tools that are now available,
including free ones and paid ones. Load
up any writing or journal entries or any
other material that you have to give it
some context. ask it some of the
coaching style questions that you saw
here. And I would really love it if you
shared in the comments below what your
experience was and what it came up with.
If you'd like to receive more
educational content on AI technology
generally and many other topics from me,
I really encourage you to sign up to our
newsletter which goes out every Tuesday
morning at this QR code or in the
description below.
I
decided in this video
I'm Okay, so this last
bast Okay, so this last b last last
batch last batch.